# KRISTINA ULICNA

PhD Candidate (penultimate year)

@ University College London

• London, United Kingdom

kristina.smith.ulicna@gmail.com

+44(0)7754385111 (UK)

in linkedin.com/in/KristinaUlicna

twitter.com/KristinaUlicna

github.com/KristinaUlicna

# Computer Skills

Strongest programming language: Python

- Machine learning libraries: skimage, sklearn, tensorflow 2.0, keras, CSBDeep
- Standard & scientific libraries: jupyter notebooks, numpy, scipy, pandas, json, matplotlib, pyplot, plotly, h5py, xml.tree

Work comfortably in **LaTeX** (with overleaf), & **Sigmaplot Statistics** (t-test, ANOVA)

#### Analysis of **DNA sequencing** data:

- SnapGene software: vector construction
- CLC workbench: Sanger sequencing
- Nanopore sequencing platform interface

# Laboratory Skills

### Molecular biology & vector construction:

- PCR (also colony, sequential, nested)
- Plasmid preparation (mini- & midi-prep)
- · Restriction endonuclease gene cloning
- Gateway cloning & Gibson Assembly
- · Preparation & purification of mRNA
- Cell-free protein synthesis (PURExpress)

#### Cell engineering & tissue culture:

- Stable cell transfection via lipofection & lentiviral & retroviral transduction
- Colony selection with titrated antibiotics
- Tet(Dox)-inducible gene expression
- Cell fractionation & organelle isolation
- Induction of cell differentiation (DMSO)
- Cell culture (passaging) with cell lines: HeLa, HL60, CH0, HEK-293, MCF-7 / 10A, MDA-MB-231, HMLER, LNCaP, HaCaT

#### Cell-based assays & imaging platforms:

- Cell proliferation assay (IncuCyte ZOOM live-cell analysis system)
- Colorimetric cell viability assay (MTT)
- Ratiometric [Ca<sup>2+</sup>] release assay (Fura-2)
- Fluorimetric Cat-S release assay (MCA)

## Gene expression detection methods:

- Primer-based reverse-transcription PCR
- · SDS-PAGE, Western (dot) blotting
- Immunocytochemistry (IF cell staining)
- Extra- & intracellular flow cytometry
- Fluorescence-activated cell sorting & FACS-sorted clonal cell line expansion

#### Summary

As a **PhD researcher** at UCL, I apply my **programming & laboratory skills** in a multi-disciplinary project combining cancer cell biology, computational single-cell tracking & **deep learning**. I focus on **Python software development** for **large data analysis** to identify biological patterns influencing **cancer cell cycling** control mechanisms. I am a practical, detail-oriented scientist with **cell engineering** background & **leadership skills** demonstrated in individual & collective settings, which I gained through work experience in **biomedical research** groups in **academia** & **industry** in the UK & US, and through my involvement in **volunteering & community projects**.

#### Education

#### Oct 2018 -Sep 2022 (expected)

## PhD in Biosciences, BBSRC LIDo DTP Programme, UCL | London, UK

- Provisional <u>Thesis</u> Title: "Deep Lineage with Deep Learning: Tracking Single-Cell Heterogeneity within Non-/Cancer Cell Lines", advised by G. Charras & A. Lowe
- Fully funded via London Interdisciplinary Doctoral Training Partnership (LIDo DTP)
- Active collaboration: Biological Physics Theory group, Carnegie Mellon University
- Yale Stem Cell Center Yale School of Medicine exchange visitor (postponed to '21)
- Merit-based Scholarships: Talents of the New Europe '19, Students to the World '19

#### Sep 2014 -Jul 2018

## BSc Biomedical Science (Hons), King's College London | London, UK

- First Class Hons (76%) Biomedical Science with Extramural Year in Pharmacology
- Awards & Scholarships: Desmond Tutu Scholarship '14, Best Lay Article Award '15

# Research Experience

#### Mar 2019 – Present

# PhD Researcher, the "DeepTree" project @ UCL | London, UK

- Ulicna K., Vallardi G., Charras G. & Lowe A. R. (2020). Automated deep lineage tree analysis using a Bayesian single cell tracking approach. bioRxiv 2020.09.10.276980
- Co-developed a robust, supervision-free, deep learning-based tracking pipeline for deep lineage analysis of large time-lapse microscopy data in non-/cancer cell lines
- Prepared publication manuscript outlining <u>computational framework</u> (U-Net, CNN, bTrack multi-object tracking algorithm) & its applicability for cell cycle research
- Analysed multigenerational lineage trees (>20,000 single cells) to identify heritable proliferation characteristics which predispose cell to acquire cancer-like properties

#### Sep 2016 -Aug 2017

# Industrial Trainee @ Crescendo Biologics Ltd.

| Cambridge, UK

- Engineered novel, universal tool cell line for early drug discovery, i.e. phage display selection & functional screening of antibody fragment oncology therapeutics
- Presented project outcomes to senior scientists & company management board

#### Jun 2016 -Sep 2016

#### Research Intern, CRUK @ University of Cambridge | Cambridge, UK

 S. Bohndiek Lab: Characterised anti-angiogenic drug effects via breast cancer cell-based growth, viability assays to evaluate oxygen role in cancer progression

# Jun 2015 -Aug 2015

# Visiting Scholar, Whitehead Institute @ MIT | Cambridge, USA

 R. Weinberg's Lab: Investigated determinants of cancer cell invasion, metastasis & tumour stroma immunomodulation upon epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition

# **Teaching Experience**

#### Jun 2020

#### "Introduction to Deep Learning" @ UCL Cancer Domain | London, UK

- Delivered a beginner-friendly <u>masterclass</u> for 100+ interdisciplinary scientists with real-life examples of deep learning-based bioimage analysis from my PhD project
- Demonstrated deep learning benefits, contrasted deep learning to computer vision methods, emphasised fundamentals of 'learning' component & current challenges

#### Mar 2020

#### Graduate Teaching Assistant, BIOC0016 module @ UCL | London, UK

- Co-designed an iPython-based <u>practical session</u> for 70+ undergraduate students for introductory concepts in bioimage analysis, bioinformatics & machine learning
- Tutored students to hand-label mini-dataset & train simplified CNN to classify cell mitotic state based on chromatin condensation level from fluorescence readouts

#### Leadership & Teamwork Experience

#### Sep 2019 -Present

# Student Ambassador, LIDo PhD Programme @ UCL | London, UK

- Outlined programme structure & shared own experience with new student cohorts
   Outlided individual structure through respectivities with eleganging retation projects.
- Guided individual students through responsibilities with changing rotation projects

#### Jul 2019

#### Rotating Delegate @ The European Union Council | Helsinki, Finland

· Shortlisted by Slovak Youth Council as representative at EU Youth Conference series

#### Aug 2017

#### Young Delegate, Youth Assembly @ United Nations | New York, USA

Selected on basis of volunteering activity & community service project involvement

# Language Skills

native proficiency Czech bilingual proficiency

full professional proficiency English 

IELTS & iBT TOEFL language test certificates

limited working proficiency 

High-school certificate; German evening classes

#### Hobbies & Interests —

- · Ballroom dancing; standard & Latin style (UK national partner competitions level)
- Bachata & salsa social dancing (int/adv)
- Long-distance running (half-marathons)
- Playing tennis (competitively at school)
- 'Stress-release' boxing & martial arts

#### General -

- Member of the London Stem Cell Network (since Dec 2019)
- Member of the University of London DanceSport Society (since Sep 2019)
- Member of the British Pharmacological Society (since Sep 2017)
- Slovak (European Union) driving licence | *B type* (since Jun 2013)
- First aid training course certificate (Mar 2013)

#### Academic Referees

#### **Prof Guillaume Charras**

- PhD project advisor; Professor in Cell & Tissue Biophysics @ London Centre for Nanotechnology & Dept. of Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- Web: https://charraslab.com/ g.charras@ucl.ac.uk Email:

#### Dr Alan R. Lowe

- PhD project advisor; Al for Science Fellow @ The Alan Turing Institute & Associate Professor of Biophysics at Inst. of Struct. & Molec. Biology @ UCL
- http://lowe.cs.ucl.ac.uk/ Weh:
- a.lowe@ucl.ac.uk Email:

#### **Prof Geraint Thomas**

- LIDo PhD Programme Deputy Director; Professor of Biochemistry at Dept. of Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- https://www.lido-dtp.ac.uk/ Weh:
- g.thomas@ucl.ac.uk Email:

# Leadership & Teamwork Experience (cont'd)

Mar 2017	Category Finalist, Telegraph STEM Awards @ GSK   London, UK • Presented an early-stage healthcare team invention pitch to expert industry judges	
2015 - 2017	Jury Member, LEAF Award @ LEAF   Bratislava, Slovakia  • Shortlisted self-driven, talented students with community involvement in jury team	
2016 - 2018	University Mentor, Talent Guide @ LEAF   Bratislava, Slovakia  • Counselled college choices with gifted high-schoolers & edited personal statements	

Specialist T	rainings & Summer Schools	
Dec 2019 - Jan 2020	Jumping Rivers Ltd.  • Two intermediate courses: 'Machine Learning with Py	<b>London, UK</b> thon' , 'Python & Tensorflow'
Aug - Sep 2019	University of Hong Kong • Practical course 'Advanced Imaging: Deep Learning in	Hong Kong, China Live Imaging & Cell Biology
Jun - Jul 2019	University of Genova • 'Machine Learning Crash Course' covering theoretical	<b>Genova, Italy</b> foundations & core concepts
Sep - Oct 2016	University of Cambridge  • Two beginners courses: 'Solving Biological Problems',	Cambridge, UK 'Statistical Analysis' using R
Jun – Jul 2012	Johns Hopkins University • Interactive class 'The History of Disease' by Centre for	Baltimore, USA Talented Youth (CTY JHU)

#### Contributed & Invited Talks

Contributed Talks: with research project "Deep Lineage with Deep Learning - Tracking the Single-Cell Heterogeneity within Non-/Cancer Cell Populations" as a PhD research student

Mar 2021	Mozilla Festival Tech Conference         Houston, TX, USA         • "Women in Al" Panelist – "Al for Global Health" session         virtual
Feb 2021	Yale Stem Cell Centre Meeting (Guo Lab)   New Haven, CT, USA  • PhD research thesis progression update to collaborative team   virtual
Jan 2021	Imperial College London         London, UK         • Virtual Seminars in Biomedical Science         virtual
Dec 2020	London Stem Cell Network & Francis Crick Institute London Stem Cell Network 3rd Annual Symposium (poster)
Nov 2020	UCL, University of London  London, UK• UCL Bioimage Analysis Interest Group  virtual
Nov 2020	#PyLadies Dublin Meetup       Dublin, Ireland       • Python Software Foundation Pro Network Meetup       virtual
Oct 2020	UK Dementia Research Institute Imperial Department of Brain Sciences Neurogenomics Seminar I virtual
Sep 2020	Society of Biomolecular Imaging & Informatics (SBI2)   Boston, MA, USA • SBI2 High Content 2020 7th Annual Conference   virtual
Jun 2020	<ul> <li>UCL &amp; Birkbeck, University of London   London, UK</li> <li>Institute of Structural &amp; Molecular Biology Postgraduate Symposium   virtual</li> </ul>
Nov 2019	Birkbeck, University of London   London, UK • Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Friday Wrap Talk
Oct 2019	King's College London   London, UK - Quantitative Systems Biology Workshop 2019
Feb 2019	Francis Crick Institute   London, UK • Francis Crick Institute & UCL Graduate Student Symposium (poster)

Invited Talks: with research project "Lipoproteins as a Vehicle for Targeted Drug Delivery

in Photodynamic	n Photodynamic Therapy of Cancer" as a pre-college student with university collaboration		
Sep 2015	Universal Expo Milano 2015 • Presented ongoing research as national team member to	<b>Milan, Italy</b> expert & lay audience	
May 2014	Intel International Science & Engineering Fair • Shortlisted finalist at world's largest pre-college science co	Los Angeles, USA   bmpetition (poster talk)	
Jul 2013	International Congress of Young Investigators • Invited as 'Absolute Winner at the Festival of Science & of 'The Special Award by the Dean of the Faculty of Nature		
Nov 2012	Festival of Science & Technology  Recognised as 'Best Scientific Project at Festival of Scientific Project at Festival	Bratislava, Slovakia   ce & Technology 2012'	

# Selected Publications

Ulicna, K., Vallardi, G., Charras, G. & Lowe, A. R. (2020). Automated deep lineage tree analysis using a Bayesian single cell tracking approach. bioRxiv 2020.09.10.276980 DOI: 10.1101/2020.09.10.276980 | GitHub: https://github.com/KristinaUlicna/DeepTree